"Is FDA-Approved Bioidentical Hormone
Replacement Therapy Safe?"
The news that
menopausal hormone therapy
had the potential to cause
higher rates of breast cancer,
cardiovascular disease,
and overall harm
rocked women and physicians
across the country.
The study arm used progesterone
and Premarin,
because it was the most commonly
prescribed form of estrogen
and is still prescribed
more than a million times
a year in the U.S.
It's a mixture of more
than 50 different estrogens
from horse pee.
("Premarin" comes from the words
"pregnant mare urine,"
if you're skeptical,
try crushing a pill
and sniffing it.)
The dour findings
of the Women's Health Initiative
(combined with some high-profile
celebrity endorsements)
saw interest shift
to "bioidentical hormones,"
made from plants
rather than a horse source.
They are marketed as being safer
and more effective.
No wonder estimates
peg the annual number
of prescriptions
at 30 million a year,
constituting
a billion-dollar industry.
One reason patients may believe
compounded hormone therapy
is safer is that,
thanks to a legal loophole,
they are not mandated
to provide
the FDA insert required
for commercial products
warning about side effects.
Purchased at regular pharmacies,
hormones have
a prominent black box
with an all-caps
"WARNING: ENDOMETRIAL CANCER,
CARDIOVASCULAR DISORDERS,
BREAST CANCER,
AND PROBABLE DEMENTIA."
There's no evidence
that bioidentical hormones
are any safer,
but the missing laundry list
of side effects
may give patients
a false sense of security.
Another appeal
is customized dosing
based on saliva hormone testing,
but such tests are considered
to be unreliable
and so recommended against,
since the only people
who profit
are the ones
trying to sell you the tests.
Custom-compounded hormones
are not FDA-approved,
have not been shown to be safer
or more effective,
and may lack standardization
of quality, purity, and dose.
When the FDA
or muckraking journalists
have filled
the same prescriptions
in compounding pharmacies
in different states,
a third of the stated
estrogen contents
were off
by as much as 250 percent.
No wonder all the major
American medical societies
that counsel physicians
on treating menopausal women
recommend against
compounded hormones,
including the American College
of Obstetrics and Gynecology,
the Endocrine Society,
and the North American
Menopause Society.
Characterizing the pushback
they got from their 2020 review
recommending against the use
of bioidentical hormones,
the National Academies
of Sciences,
Engineering,
and Medicine concluded,
"It is clear
from these communications
that many clinicians,
compounding pharmacists,
and patients hold minimum,
if any,
concerns regarding
the medication's safety
and effectiveness."
Now, as of 2019,
there are pee-free FDA-approved
bioidentical hormones
that skirt
the standardization concerns
of compounded preparations,
but that just brings us back
to square one,
since they are considered
to have
the same risk/benefit profile.
The multibillion-dollar
compounded hormone industry
is considered a "leading source
of disinformation,"
but the same could be said
of Big Pharma.
With so many billions of dollars
at stake,
it's hard to know
who to trust.
When in doubt,
I turn to The Medical Letter
on Drugs and Therapeutics,
considered one
of the least biased sources
in medicine.
It's kind of like
the Consumer Reports
of the drug world,
and, in fact,
was actually co-founded
by the co-founder
of the publisher
of Consumer Reports
more than 50 years ago.
As The Medical Letter
used to brag on their website,
it "does not accept grants,
from any source;
donations, from anyone;
[or] funding, from any entity."
They won't let their work be
used for promotional purposes,
and they don't accept
any advertising.
In their review of the evidence,
they concluded,
"There is no acceptable evidence
that bio-identical hormones
are safer."
So, how do you treat
menopausal symptoms
like hot flashes?
The American College of
Obstetricians and Gynecologists
suggests palliative measures,
such as "consuming cool drinks,"
but is there really no way
to treat hot flashes
without the cancer, clots,
and coronaries?
Thankfully there is,
as I cover in a video series
that starts with
Menopausal Hot Flashes
Are Not Inevitable
and then moves
from prevention to treatment.